[R STUDIO SOUND BITE]
ANNOUNCER: So
without further ado,
I'd like to introduce
our first speaker,
Will Chase, speaking on
the glamour of graphics.
[APPLAUSE]
WILL CHASE: All right, so thank
you for coming today everyone.
And welcome to my
talk on the glamour
of graphics, which is a talk
on the design of charts.
So if you recognize me,
it's probably from Twitter.
I tweet excessively.
And you may also
recognize my website,
williamrchase.com,
where I post lots
of blogs about art
and generative art--
how to make it in
R, R tutorials,
all sorts of stuff like that.
So professionally, I
come from academia.
I worked at Penn State and
then U Penn for many years.
And now, recently, I've
joined Fidelity Investments
as a Senior
Visualization Analyst
where I'm focusing on visual
design and storytelling
within our organization.
I also do freelance
data visualization.
So if you're interested
in talking about that,
please get in touch.
Now the glamour of
graphics that I'm
going to be talking about
today it was actually
inspired by Kelly Bodwin.
As I say, I tweet excessively.
So this is where I
got the inspiration.
And that led me to spend
one of my Saturdays
making this Glamour
Magazine spoof
which I think was probably
my most viral tweet ever.
And I may be the
first person to get
invited to talk at RStudio
conf based on a Twitter meme
that I made.
So I'm pretty proud of that.
But I think that there's
actually some substance here.
So this said "Take your
charts from drab to fab".
And that's sort of what we're
going to try to do today.
So this is the drab.
This is the starting
point, right?
Sorry, Hadley, but it's true.
What we're going to try to do
is get something more like this.
So a little bit about
what this talk is not it's
not a talk about chart shaming.
So you'll see a lot
of design mistakes
that I'm going to
talk about today.
But if you go to my blog
and look at my portfolio,
you will see all of
those mistakes featured
heavily there.
It's also not a talk
about tools or about what
charts to use in terms of,
like, data visualization.
It's really focused
on the aesthetics.
So the reason you should care
about aesthetics in charts
is pretty obvious to me.
But it will help you engage
a much wider audience
with your work.
It'll actually help your
work to be perceived as more
usable and more intuitive.
So it's actually been shown
that charts that are more
aesthetically
pleasing are perceived
by users to be more intuitive.
And finally, they'll
just let you show respect
for your audience.
You know, people spend their
time looking at your charts.
You should spend time
making them look nice.
So when I started
researching this,
I thought it was sort of just
a coincidence-- of grammar
of graphics, glamour
of graphics, haha.
But it turns out that the
word glamour is actually
derived from the word grammar.
So back in the Middle
Ages, the word grammar
meant all learning.
And that included things
like magic and occult.
And through the ages, that word
sort of morphed into glamour.
And as it did it lost the
association with knowledge
and it became to mean just
a magical spell actually.
And then eventually,
in the 18th century,
the idea of magic sort of
washed away a little bit.
And we got the
meaning that we know
today which is the sort of
exciting, illusory, romantic
attractiveness.
So the grammar of
graphics is a tool
that enables us to
concisely describe
the components of a graphic.
And what I'm going
to do today is
try to bring this sort of
illusory, romantic quality
of glamour a little bit
closer to a grammar.
So I'm going to
describe a tool that
enables us to concisely describe
the design of a graphic.
So in the grammar
of graphics, we
have these three components of
data aesthetics and geometries
that are really the
core of any chart.
And I know there's more layers.
But this is really the core
of how to describe a chart.
What I'm going to describe
in the glamour of graphics
is similar.
But I'm going to
describe three layers
that you need to describe
the design of a graphic.
And that's the layout, the
typography, and the color.
So beginning with
layout, I'm going
to talk about three
main concepts today.
And that is alignment,
whitespace, and grids, lines,
and borders.
So beginning with
alignment, I want
to talk about titles first.
Titles should be
top-left aligned usually.
And when I say
top-left aligned, I
don't mean the case
that you see on the left
where you have left
aligned with your data.
I mean left aligned all the
way to the edge of your chart
to create a nice clean line
with the edge of your chart.
Now previously,
this was actually
kind of tricky to do
with ggplot but luckily
in the development
version we have
a new argument that makes
this very, very simple to do.
Next I want you
to please not make
me do like this when
I read your chart.
So I see this a lot
of times, especially
in academic graphics where you
have these really long x-axis
labels.
Nobody wants to do that.
So, of course,
it's always better
if you can to flip our
coordinates horizontally.
Or if you can't
manage to flip it,
you can just try to make the
text horizontal by increasing
your spacing and such.
This is a little more
controversial, maybe,
but I also think it's
actually best practice
not to use vertical
axis labels because you
have the same problem.
So you can do the same thing.
You can try to make the
text just horizontal.
Or a lot of times you can get
rid of axis labels entirely.
A lot of axis labels are
completely unnecessary-- things
like dates.
In this case, SUV, minivan--
it's obvious these
are types of cars.
And usually by just
including a good title,
you can do away
with axis labels.
So when you're thinking
about alignment,
you should always try to create
clean lines and symmetry.
And what I want to go
over is a little bit--
this graphic from 538
that I think really
illustrates some
of these points.
So this doesn't have
big blocks of text.
But just to mention, if you
do have big blocks of text
like an infographic
or something,
you want to left align
those most likely.
Left alignment should
sort of be your default.
Right alignment can be used
for labels a lot of times,
so especially like
horizontal bar labels where
the goal is to
create a clean line
with the edge of your data.
And sometimes
subtitles or labels
can be center aligned if
it helps to create symmetry
within the graphic.
So in this case, you can
see actually the designer
made a mistake on the 2014 one.
It should be center aligned.
But it's slightly off center.
But if you look at the
rest of the graphic,
you can see how this left
alignment, right alignment,
and center alignment sort of
creates this perfect symmetry
within the graphic.
So charts often come with
these extraneous elements.
They're not data.
And a lot of times, they
can distract from the chart.
So I want to talk a little
bit about how to reduce those.
A good example of
this is borders.
You almost never need
a border in a chart.
Oftentimes, they just
don't serve a purpose.
And all they do is
distract from your data--
add ink to the page.
Another thing is grid lines.
I understand that
there's reasons
to have grid lines sometimes.
But I encourage you
to always question
the purpose of every grid line.
Do you need horizontal
grid lines in every case?
Do you need minor grid lines?
If not, please remove them.
If you do need them,
I encourage you
to make them as light
and as small as possible
so that they sort of
disappear into the background
rather than distracting
from your data.
Another thing that distracts
from your data a lot
is legends,
particularly when you
have like a big blob of a legend
off to the right-hand side
of your chart.
It's not a very good
flow within your chart.
So I recommend, if
you have legends,
you put them right
below the titles
where it creates a nice
flow with your chart.
A better solution even is
to directly label your data.
Or my favorite solution
is to use colored text
to indicate your
legend in the title.
And this will now be possible
with the new gridtext
package, which I think Claus is
talking about this afternoon.
So a few words about whitespace.
This is particularly
relevant when
you're looking at things like
dashboards and infographics
where you're laying out
a lot of charts together.
And what I often
see is people want
to cram as much information
as they can possibly
get onto the page.
But what that ends
up resulting in
is that you can't even
understand any of it.
Your eye has no idea
where to go on the page.
And so your charts really
need room to breathe.
So I always recommend
it's like garlic--
you take as much white
space as you think you need,
and then triple it.
So that's sort of the
foundation of building
a nice chart is the layout.
And next up, I'm going
to talk about typography.
So typography is a very
sort of vast subject.
It has a lot of details in it.
And I can't cover
them all today.
But what I highly,
highly recommend
you do is go to
practicaltypography.com.
This is a completely free,
open-source online book
that will basically
teach you everything
you could need to
know about typography
in a very concise way.
It'll take about three hours
to read cover to cover.
And it will vastly improve
the design of everything
that you write.
But I do want to touch a
little bit on fonts, hierarchy,
and a couple of dataviz
specific concerns.
So the font that you choose
really matters in a chart.
It especially affects the
tone of your graphic, right?
You can send a completely
different message
based on the font you choose.
And it can also really affect
the legibility of your graphic,
right?
It's pretty easy to
have misunderstandings
if you choose the wrong font.
This is important.
And the unfortunate thing is
that most people will just
go for the system
font-- the default font.
And that's sad because
most system fonts
are pretty terrible.
I'm sorry to tell you.
Most of them were
designed for the screens
that we had in the
1990s, which were
all pixilated and terrible.
And on modern screens,
they look pretty ugly.
So if you're a
professional organization,
you might buy a
professional font.
But for most of you
in the room, you'll
probably be looking
at free fonts.
And the good news
is that, in 2020, we
have a wealth of wonderfully
designed, beautiful, free
fonts available easily
at fonts.google.com.
These are some of my favorites
for data visualization.
I really like the
Source family it
has a sans serif variety, serif
variety, mono spaced variety.
And they're all available and
lots of weights and sizes.
So next, I want to touch a
little bit upon hierarchy--
a typographic hierarchy.
So a typographic
hierarchy is just
a way of encoding an
order of importance
in your type that
helps to navigate
your readers through your
chart or through your document.
And there's several ways
to create hierarchy.
So this is a case
where we have none.
The easiest way to create
hierarchy is with size.
But you can also do
it with font weight,
with color, with spacing.
You can do it with a
contrasting typeface,
or, ideally, a combination
of all of these things.
And learning the rules of
how to create a hierarchy,
you know, what should
you make your title
versus your subtitle
versus your body text
is just a skill that takes
a little bit of practice.
But there are some
more specific tips
in the practical typography
book that I mentioned earlier.
And finally, I want to talk
about numbers a little bit.
So we use numbers all the
time in data visualization.
Some fonts have what's
called old style numbers.
I recommend do not use these.
Most of those fonts will also
have lining numbers, which
have all the same x height.
And in a similar
vein, you also want
to choose a font that
has tabular numbers.
Tabular numbers all
have the same width
so that when you make
a table or something,
everything will line up
in a nice perfect column.
So having covered the layout
and the typography of a chart,
I want to talk a little
bit about the color--
everyone's favorite topic.
So there's a lot
of tools out there.
I know people are probably
familiar with things like
colorbrewer and there's other R
packages that will basically
just choose a color for you--
choose a color palette for you.
What I want to do today
is try to give you
a little bit of information
that will hopefully
help you to choose your
own color palettes.
The truth is, though,
that color is really hard.
So I don't want to lie
to you and tell you
it's going to be easy.
It's something I
still struggle with.
And it's just such
a complex subject
that it takes a lot of practice.
But, I think there are a few
things that I can tell you
today about color
theory and then
a few sort of
practical tips to help
improve your usage of color.
So one of the chief complaints
I get from people is they say,
I just don't know what
colors look good together.
How do I know what
looks good together?
This is a case where the color
wheel can really help you.
So the color wheel like we
all know from grade school--
it looks like this.
And there's several
types of palettes
you can choose from the color
wheel that will usually have
colors that go well together.
So if you want to choose
a high contrast palette,
you can choose a
complementary one.
That means opposite
sides of the color wheel.
You can also choose
analogous color palettes
which all come from the same
side of the color wheel.
And there's triadic which
are sort of laid out
in a triangle like this.
And there's several other
color palettes as well.
There's split complementary,
quadratic, and lots of others.
And you can read a little bit
more about sort of the feeling
that all these color
palettes give you.
But this is a nice way to
sort of get started if you're
looking to choose some hues.
So once you choose
those, you might
want to adjust your
colors a little bit.
And I want to highlight
the HSL color space.
So this is a way of
describing color in contrast
to something like RGB.
HSL stands for the hue,
saturation, and lightness
of a color.
So the hue is the
actual color itself--
red, green, blue.
The saturation is the amount
of color you have there.
And the lightness is how
light or dark a color is.
So this is an example
where we have a red hue.
And if we turn
down the saturation
you can see that it'll basically
drain all the color out
of there.
It's very dull.
If we turn up the
saturation, it's
going to become very
rich and vibrant.
And if we turn
down the lightness,
we can see we still
have a richness here.
But now it's much darker.
And if we turn it up, it'll
become more lighter obviously.
But you can see how this
is a very easy way when
you pick a color and
you say, oh but I
wish it were a little bit
lighter or a little bit more
saturated or less saturated.
This is a much more
intuitive mental model
I think of how to
adjust your colors.
And there's lots
of online tools you
can use where you
can stick it in
and it'll sort of allow
you to adjust the sliders
a little bit for your saturation
and lightness and such.
So that was a little
bit of the color theory.
Now some other practicalities
of how I choose color.
So I'm sort of a color pirate.
I use my favorite tool in
the world all the time,
which is the eyedropper tool.
So this is a tool if
you're not familiar-- it's
present in all kinds
of design programs.
And you can get apps
on your computer.
On my Mac, I like to use
one called Color Slurp.
On Windows, I like Instant
Eyedropper where you can just
click the tool, pick any
pixel on your screen,
and will return
the color for you.
So I use this all the time.
If I see a data
visualization, for example,
that I really like where
I love the color palette.
I'll just take my eyedropper,
pick those colors.
I do this with websites,
with photographs.
And then I use the HSL
sliders to adjust the colors
afterwards.
A good example of this is this
generative conference badge
that I designed this summer.
And I got the inspiration
from my mom's day planner.
I went to visit my parents
and saw this day planner.
And I really liked it so I
just took a picture of it.
And when it came time
to design the graphic,
I took my eyedropper tool,
picked all the colors I liked,
adjusted them a little
bit with the HSL sliders,
and then had my color palette.
And finally, I want to talk a
little bit about backgrounds.
So one thing I actually like
a lot about the default ggplot
theme is that it doesn't
use a white background.
White backgrounds
are not terrible.
There's lots of-- you know,
there's a time and place.
But I think they're very
overused, especially
because white is a very
harsh color especially
on digital screens.
White is a very aggressive
and bright color.
So I encourage you to sort of
not necessarily go straight
to white as a
background as a default.
And instead, explore
some other options.
Recently I've really liked
this sort of ivory color.
A light gray color
can also be very nice.
Or dark backgrounds are
fun to experiment with.
But if you do go with
a dark background,
just like I don't recommend
a pure white background all
the time, I would be
careful unless you
have a specific
reason about choosing
a pure black background.
So to review a
little bit, I have
talked about how
you can establish
a good layout in your
data visualizations
by creating clean
lines and symmetry,
reducing clutter, and
increasing white space.
And you can use good fonts,
not use system fonts,
and establish a
typographic hierarchy
to help guide readers
through your visualization.
And then, hopefully,
I have given you
a little bit of
the tools that you
need to start coming up
with your own palettes
and choosing your
own color palettes.
And with that, I
will say thank you.
And that's it.
[APPLAUSE]
ANNOUNCER: Thanks so much, Will.
I have questions
from the audience,
while Tyler, you can come get
set up a little if you want.
The first one is, do you have
any specific recommendations
for aesthetics for maps?
WILL CHASE:
Aesthetics for maps-
I mean, essentially all the
same rules apply, right?
Maps you want to
try to reduce a lot
of times the
extraneous elements.
So maps often have a lot of
extraneous elements and borders
and such.
And sometimes you're
going for a thematic map.
You actually might want
to emphasize those.
But if you're trying to go for
a very clean, easy to read map,
you have to think about that.
There's also a lot
to be considered
in maps with iconography.
So using proper icons
that help readers identify
whatever you're looking for
or using a really careful type
hierarchy.
So you have to really, really
be careful about your type
hierarchy and spend a lot of
time designing that for a map
since you have so many
labels and so much type.
ANNOUNCER: Next one is shouldn't
a binding constraint for color
be color blind friendliness?
WILL CHASE: Yes,
absolutely it should.
I didn't have time
to talk about this.
One of my slides
got cut for time.
But another very important
thing to do in color
is accessibility.
So you should always be
checking your color palettes
for color blindness
and also for contrast.
And there's easy websites
where you can do that.
ANNOUNCER: Why is it
better for a title
to be left aligned
instead of centered?
WILL CHASE: The reason is mainly
because, in Western countries
at least, humans read
from the top left.
So that's where your eye
goes first on the page.
There's several eye
tracking studies
that show that
your eye goes first
to the top left of the page and
then to the middle of the page.
And so putting the
title at the top left
is basically reducing
the amount of work
that the reader has to do
to get to the information.
ANNOUNCER: Couple more-- how
long should one typically spend
on creating/designing a chart?
How long does it typically
take you to create one?
WILL CHASE: To create a
simple design, like something
I would do for
Fidelity, you know,
something that just needs to
look clean and and readable, I
spend, I don't know, maybe a
couple hours designing a chart.
If I'm designing
something more thematic
or something sort of a
personal project, something
more creative, I mean,
it can take months.
You know it's not all
a month of sitting down
just like designing nonstop
for eight hours a day.
But it's months of like
laying in bed at 4:00 AM
thinking about colors.
ANNOUNCER: That's it.
Thoughts on Tufte theme charts--
WILL CHASE: I like it.
ANNOUNCER: --question mark.
WILL CHASE: That's all I'll say.
ANNOUNCER: Great,
and then oh, what
tool has been used for creating
the presentation slides?
WILL CHASE: The
presentation slides
were created with Keynote.
And let me emphasize,
actually, I want to clarify.
I like the Tufte
R Markdown theme.
I don't always agree with
everything Tufte says.
So Tufte-- if you read
like his dataviz books,
he has a lot of opinions.
I don't agree with all of those.
But there is a Tufte
R Markdown theme
that's based on some of his
writings which I really like.
ANNOUNCER: And then
the last one before we
let Tyler get
going is how do you
deal with viewers using monitors
that might render colors
slightly differently?
WILL CHASE: Yeah
it's a good question.
I mean, there's very little you
can do about that to be honest.
I don't have a magical solution
to change everyone's monitors
for you.
All I can say is that we are
lucky to live in 2020 when
people have--
most people have more
high resolution monitors.
So we can use things
like fonts that
have a lot of details
in them and, you know,
nice color palettes.
But it's tricky.
ANNOUNCER: Well,
thank you so much.
Another round of
applause for Will.
WILL CHASE: All right, thanks.
[APPLAUSE]
[R STUDIO SOUND BITE]