Good morning and welcome
back to RStudio Conf.
It's really--
[APPLAUSE]
It's really great to
see you all here again,
whether it's in person or
on one of our livestreams.
But now it's my very
great honor to introduce
our next keynote speaker,
my colleague and friend,
Jenny Bryan.
[APPLAUSE]
Jenny's work has
almost certainly
touched you in some
way, whether it's
one of her books like
Happy Git With R or R,
What They Forgot to Teach You.
Or perhaps it's because
you're afraid that she'll
set your computer on fire
because you  "setwd()".
But-- or maybe you're
using one of her packages,
like readxl or googlesheets
to get data out
of spreadsheets, whether it's
Excel or Google, and into R.
But of all the packages, of all
the work that Jenny has done,
I think my favorite package
is the reprex package.
Not only because it's
such a great tool to help
you get help from other people.
But I think it's one of
the rare packages that
has no precedent in
any other package,
in any other
programming language.
It's something
that's genuinely new.
So without further ado, I'd
like to welcome Jenny Bryan.
[APPLAUSE]
JENNY BRYAN: So this, I think,
is R's most infamous error
message, object of type
closure is not subsettable.
It was my title, as
a joke, for a while.
And then people thought I
should actually stick with it.
So I have 20 years of
experience triggering
this bug, which is why I can
now do it in two lines of code.
And this is also, I
think, commonly how
it actually happens,
although it's usually never
quite this clear.
But you create your
main data object.
You call it dat.
Then you promptly lose all
memory of having done so.
And you ask for the x column
of df, which you haven't made.
But df exists.
It's a function that gives
you the density of the F
distribution.
So what you've asked
for makes no sense,
and R tells you this in
this very special way.
And my sort of fantasy
message down there
is maybe it would be able to
somehow read my mind, which is
obviously not going to happen.
And so this sets the mood
for the next hour, where
I want to talk about
general strategies
for coping with confusing
and frustrating situations.
So you went into data science.
You were probably told that
it's going to be glamor and fun,
like, 24/7.
And you would make very creative
concoctions that you present,
and people love to consume it.
But there's all this
drudgery, as there
is in any job, where
we actually spend
a much greater proportion of
our time and our mental energy.
And so I've sort of made a
habit of talking and teaching
about those things so that you
feel really cool and have fun,
but you get your
drudgery done as well.
So we're not using Slido
for live questions,
although you're welcome to
ask them because I'm going
to blog about this talk later.
But I am using Slido
live for some polls.
So if you're willing to get
your laptop or your computer
out, your phone out,
I'm curious what
your current main
debugging method is.
And if you use multiple,
as you probably do,
you will have to
pick a favorite.
And while I'm letting
you take this poll,
I'm going to say
a few more words
about why I think this is so
important, the drudgery part.
So, we don't give a name to these
things and give them dignity.
When you lose half of your day
to doing something like this,
it's extremely
demotivating because you
feel like you haven't actually
gotten any real work done.
And the other risk,
especially with debugging,
is if you're only
reactive and you're always
dealing with today's bug, it
means that you are constantly
putting out fires, and you
don't probably have the time
at that point to take--
to develop your debugging
skills and be a little bit
proactive about it.
But you shouldn't be
perpetually surprised
that there's a new bug.
Like, really, again?
Today?
This is going to
happen every day,
and it's actually worth
giving some thought
to how you want to do things.
So let's see if
anyone's responded.
I think they have.
But it's difficult for
me to refresh over here.
It's a very complicated
problem with how
I'm using this computer.
So I am going to
keep taking polls.
And I am not going to
show you the results.
And I will assume they are
what I think they should be,
which is that it's probably
all over the map there.
I will reveal this in the
promised blog post as well.
So here's where
we're going to go.
There's four sections
of this talk.
And I hope that there's
something for everyone
here, depending on
your R experience can
be quite little or quite a lot.
And there'll be
something that you
find interesting useful,
or at least makes you feel
very validated in what you do.
And this is also basically
approximately the order
in which I do these things.
And they do all
come up all the time
on most puzzling situations.
So the first thing
I want to talk about
is the beauty of
resetting things.
Earlier this week we
ran a ton of workshops.
I helped out in one.
I was not in charge
because I was doing this.
And this reaffirmed
my commitment
to how important
the idea of resets is
and why it really should
be your first strategy.
So as soon as you get
some sort of error,
I don't know about you,
but I immediately--
I just send that
same command again.
Because maybe it's
going to work this time.
And it does not ever, ever work.
But there is a small
variation on this
that is an extremely
productive implementation.
And it's the world's most
famous troubleshooting advice
for anything, but
especially tech,
because it's so hard
to get this right,
that you should try turning
it off and turning it
back on again.
And why is that?
So this is a super corny phrase
that we have all heard before,
that if you love something,
you need to set it free.
And if it's really
yours, it will come back.
And I think this applies
to unloved things as well.
So if you have a
strange problem,
and it just actually
doesn't make much sense,
consider setting it
free, restarting R,
and see if it comes back.
So I want you to restart
R often, and especially
when things get weird.
And you might think
I'm being glib
or I'm just trying to sweep
some problem under the rug.
But that is not actually true.
It's like one of the things
that's pretty unusual about R
is we install and
update packages from R.
And this is a little bit like
working on your airplane engine
while you're flying.
And I think people updating
and installing packages
while they're doing work
in R, and especially if they
have multiple R sessions
open, is a common reason
why things get funky in a way
that's quite difficult to debug
and understand.
And the good news is
you don't have to.
Quit, restart, and
you're guaranteed
to have the package version
that's loaded into memory
be the one that was
installed on disk.
So that's an example of why
this is a legitimate way
to reset things.
So how do we actually
do this in R?
So this is the RStudio version.
There is a menu
entry, where you can
restart R. I have this
keyboard shortcut emblazoned
into my brain.
It's something I do
many times per day.
And the second thing I
recommend that you consider--
this is kind of a
big lifestyle change,
so don't do it right now--
is to consider not reloading
your workspace at startup
and not saving
your workspace when
you quit R. It's a pretty
radical lifestyle change.
[APPLAUSE]
Yes.
And I get a lot of
push-back on this, so I
do appreciate the clapping.
I'm going to remember that when
I get this week's push-back.
This is the way to do
this if you were just
starting R in a terminal.
And I also just want to use
this as a proxy for that
figure I just showed you.
So you can start R with
command line flags,
including --no-save
and --no-restore-data.
And I want to argue
this is vastly
superior to another thing
that a lot of us do.
And I have lots of
this on my computer
from previous years, where
people use rm(list = ls()).
So that lists all the objects
in the global workspace,
and it deletes them.
And so this is a
really common command
to see at the top of R scripts.
And believe me, this was my
like 100% practice all the time.
But the problem is it
doesn't really go far enough.
So this brings me
to my next poll.
And I'm going to continue
to believe that you're all
filling out the poll.
And I want you to think
about these six R commands.
And they all have
some sort of effect.
And then let's say you execute
this command rm(list = ls()).
Which of these effects will
persist in this session
after that?
And I will give you
a minute to do this
because this one requires
a bit more thinking.
You can select-- you should
be selecting multiple answers.
And I didn't give
you permission,
but you are allowed to talk
to your neighbor, which
many of you clearly are.
We encourage that.
It's not cheating.
They're good?
OK.
I hear there are responses.
So I'm going to
do the big reveal.
So library(dplyr)
leaves dplyr attached.
So that persists after
rm(list = ls()).
Redefining the summary
function, that's been cleared.
So you have reset summary()
to its normal definition.
If you've changed an option,
like stringsAsFactors,
from true to false, that
persists in this session.
If you've changed the
language of the session,
that's going to affect what
error messages look like,
for example.
That persists.
Binding one, two,
three, four, five
to the name x, that's gone.
x is gone.
But if you've attached an
environment or a data frame
to the search path, that's
still there as well.
And so all of those four
things that persist here
aren't top of mind.
You're really thinking
about those objects.
But they all have an effect on
how your subsequent code runs.
And so this makes it
very easy to develop code
under a set of
expectations that will not
hold when someone
else runs that code
or when you are running
it in a fresh R session.
So it's for that reason
that I think starting R
in a way where you don't
reload the workspace
and you don't save it is vastly
superior to this practice,
because it's really like if you
care enough to kill your work
space, you care enough
to restart R. You should
go that far, so
fresh starts, clean
the workspace, reset options,
and environment variables,
and clear the search path.
So I want us to think of this as
your R sessions are like crops.
You grow them.
You harvest them without
any fear, not a house plant.
There's another saying
from the cloud and VM
world that's more morbid
about livestock and pets.
So this is our slightly kinder,
gentler version of that.
And this practice of having
no memory, in some sense,
of not loading your
workspace and not saving it
is pretty difficult to
implement by itself.
It really works best in
synergy with some other habits,
in particular saving your source
is obviously very important.
So source is real.
And there's some other habits
that are quite important.
So at the beginning I actually
should have mentioned this
there's an rstud.io/debugging
short link.
And that will take
you to a README
on GitHub that has a lot of
links related to the talks
that aren't in the slides,
but if you want to follow up
on some of these ideas.
So let's talk about reprex.
I'm very excited
that Hadley likes it.
And I should really-- well,
we'll get to this credit.
It's really a wrap around
things other people have made.
But it's a very handy
wrapper, I will have to say.
And I'm kind of talking
about the package,
but I really want to talk
about the reprex mindset more
than anything.
So you know that if I get a
mistake, the first thing I do
is I submit the
same command again.
The next thing you might do
is sort of brood, dither,
and fret about what
you've just seen.
And a lot of people
just immediately
go into speculating usually
about worst-case scenarios
about what could
possibly be wrong.
And this is just as effective
as submitting the same command
again, which is to say that it
is not effective in the least.
And so one good way to knock
yourself out of this paralysis
is to work a small example.
And for years, I was
a statistics professor
who cared about R, but I was
by no means a professional R
programmer.
And then over various
years, I started hanging out
more and more with the experts.
And I think I finally
crossed the line into being
one of those experts now.
And here's one of
the things I learned.
I used to think that
the experts just
knew everything all the time.
And that's not true.
They know some things for sure.
But a bigger distinction
is they have this habit
of working an example.
So if there's a really weird
situation, they test a theory,
or they gather some data.
And this is much more
approachable as a strategy
than trying to solve
all your problems.
All you have to do is
work one small example
that sheds a new
light on the problem,
confirms so-and-so's theory or
rules so-and-so's theory out.
So the term minimum reproducible
example is pre-existing.
It's important across all
programming languages.
And a minimal
reproducible example
is much beloved in places like
Stack Overflow and GitHub.
And my colleague,
Romain Francois,
decided to coin the term
reprex by mushing those two
words together.
And at that same time, I
was creating this package
mostly out of wild frustration
with code conversations
with my students.
So I used the name.
And making a reprex is
both a science and an art.
So the reproducible part
is the science part.
And that means you've provided
code that someone else could
actually run.
And that's what the reprex
package can help with.
It can only help with sort
of mechanical robotic things.
But then there's
this whole aspect
about the art of
making a reprex.
And that's making it minimal.
And only humans
really can do that.
And so that comes with having
more and more experience.
And if you can't instantly
give yourself more experience,
you can hang out in places where
you're exposed to good reprexes
all the time, and you'll
start to absorb what
the principles of that are.
So I'm about to show you a
few tiny snippets of code
that aren't quite
complete and that
recapitulate a lot
of the struggles seen
when people post examples.
And then we'll just see
a nice beautiful reprex.
So I want you to try to
run this code in your mind
and identify what
the mistake is.
Why is there an error?
And I'll give you a couple
of seconds to look at this.
So template is a string.
It's got place holders for an
exclamation and an adjective.
And then I call a
function praise() on it.
But this is not a function
in base R. So the error
that we get is that it can't
find the function praise().
So this is a
problem that you see
when people post a lot of
code, but they don't tell you
which packages they're using.
And you get to slowly
sort of figure that out
through 20 questions.
So here's another
small variant of this.
Let's run that
again in your head.
Imagine it in a fresh R session,
not the one that we just used.
So here we do remember to
attach the praise package.
And then we call
praise() on template.
But template has not
been defined here.
It might exist on
someone's computer,
whoever ran that code.
But in terms of by
the time this code
goes somewhere, again, someone
won't be able to run this.
So in this super
tiny example, this
is what a complete
reprex would look like.
We declare all of
our dependencies.
We are attaching
the praise package.
We create all of our inputs,
like this template object.
And then we do the
thing we've come to do,
which is to emit some praise.
And so making this type of
error and correction easier
is one of the main reasons
for the reprex package,
is to sort of help
people put their code
on a little spaceship
and send it somewhere
to be executed in isolation.
And so the reproducible
part is that there's
no reliance on hidden
state or secret things
that I know that you
don't know or that
are true about my R session
that aren't true about yours.
And another reason it's
incredibly important to
provide--
to express your problem
in runnable code
is because of this.
So I don't know if
you've ever tried
to help a relative with a
tech problem over the phone.
But there's what someone
thinks they're doing--
I trust everyone has
good intentions--
and what they say they're doing.
And then there's what
they're actually doing.
And quite often, this gap
between these two things,
that's where the problem is.
And so if all you're
getting is what
you think and say
you're doing, it's
incredibly hard for
someone else to maybe help
you troubleshoot things.
So by providing your minimal
reproducible examples
as runnable code, you get
rid of all sorts of opinions
people have about what's
wrong, potential for vocabulary
confusion, where
you say potato, I
say "potahto" and
this sort of stuff.
And it's much easier to figure
out what's actually going on.
So to turn back to minimal,
when you're trying to figure out
what's going on in a
confusing situation,
you can think of
it as the classic
looking for a needle
in a haystack exercise.
And so common sense
would tell you
that if you could make
that haystack smaller,
it's going to be a lot
easier to find your needle.
And this is the basic
principle behind why
making a reprex minimal
is so important.
So your goal is to
try to make the code
and the data as small
and simple as possible.
And if you took
anything else away,
it wouldn't be
making your point,
or it wouldn't show the error.
So I'm going to show
a wild-caught problem.
And this was kindly donated
by Brooke Madubuonwu,
with her permission.
And so this was a problem
she shared with me privately
at first.
And it's OK if you can't
see all of this code.
It's kind of the point.
The meta point of this slide
is that wild-caught puzzles
are complicated.
And so the main thing
you want to know here
is that this is a little
data ingest snippet.
It brings in a bunch
of Excel worksheets
that come from a bunch
of Excel workbooks,
brings everything in as a
list of many, many, many data
frames, and then turns all
the variables into character.
And then out of the bottom
pops this completely mysterious
message, error,
the dot, dot, dot
list does not contain
three elements.
So it's not at all clear
where in the pipeline
that's coming from or what
she can actually do about it.
And the thing I
want to show here--
and this was a
legitimate problem
that needed to be solved.
But this is a wild-caught
example, by definition,
probably uses private
files that only you have.
In this case, she needs 10 lines
of code to do what she's doing.
That's just the complexity
of what she's doing,
eight functions from five
different add-on packages.
So we chat a little.
And Brooke also
goes off and sort
of ruthlessly minimizes things.
And eventually this surfaces
as an issue on dplyr.
And by the time
she was done, this
is what the reprex
looked like that
enabled a coherent
conversation to happen.
And it was really more
about things were happening
in various packages,
and we gradually
got a much better
error message here.
But the key features are
that we have inline data.
She defines the
data frame there.
And she calls one function, so
inline data, not private data,
2 lines of code, not 10.
It involves one package, not
five, one function, not eight.
And this gets to the heart
of matter much quickly.
So how do you actually do this?
And I would say one
of the easiest places
to start is
simplifying the data.
So if the data that created
your problem has 500 rows,
why can't it have 499?
Why not 498?
Keep making it smaller,
and you will gradually
reveal to yourself which
features of that data frame
are important for
showing the problem.
So a minimal reprex has
small, simple inputs.
It's awesome if you can
inline them and no calls
to packages or functions
that aren't actually needed.
I watch a lot of
the repositories
for our packages on GitHub.
And there's a certain
type of notification.
Or actually, it's usually
like 100 notifications
I get at once, when
Hadley does issue triage.
And so one of the things
he will do is he'll post--
and he always says it this way,
"slightly more minimal reprex".
So I actually did it GitHub
search for that phrase
and went and looked at
these issue threads.
And this is a sketchy
diagram because I
like the way that looks.
But this is actually based
on data and a ggplot2 figure.
And I counted the lines of
code in Hadley's version
versus the original version.
And they are consistently
a lot smaller.
And this is lines of code.
But this would apply to
many measures of reprex
size, whatever that might mean.
And you might say, well,
Jenny, that's great.
Hadley had special
knowledge of these packages
and is maybe better
at this than I am.
And that is possibly true.
But I think there's
something else going
on that makes me want
to still point out
how important this is.
And there are a lot of
reasons to make a reprex.
But somehow the
discipline of knowing
that you're preparing
something to show other people
makes you get your
ducks in a row.
And it also consistently
forces you to minimize things.
And a lot of people--
the numbers vary.
I obviously made these up.
But a lot of people report
that when they finally
decide that they're going
to post something on GitHub
or Stack Overflow or RStudio's
community site, 80% to 90%
of the time they solve their
own problem because it just
got them working in
a productive way.
And that won't
happen every time.
And so when it doesn't
happen, it still
means that you have this
beautiful version of your pain
that you can post
somewhere in a way
that other people are more
likely to engage with it.
We're going to move
on, in some sense,
to the heart of the talk, maybe
what you thought it would be,
which is about proper debugging.
But I do want to say I think
the two previous things are
actually incredibly important.
They don't feel
like rocket science.
But they can prevent you from
getting to this point a lot.
But so what if you haven't
solved your own problem,
and no one stepped forward
to solve it for you?
You have no choice but
to debug it yourself.
So I'm opening another
poll that might
be a little bit
mysterious to some of you.
And we'll talk about
this again at the end.
So this will be
open for a while.
But so I want to
know if you have ever
gotten stuck R's debugger.
And answer this at will.
So this mood I
want to set here is
that this is a pretty
famous Far Side
cartoon about how
we talk to our dogs,
where we express all these
detailed emotions or detailed
instructions and we're pretty
sure that all the dog hears
is, blah, blah, blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah, Ginger.
Blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
And I think a lot of us process
error messages this way.
So this is a real error message.
It's going to strike fear in
the hearts of those of you
who can actually read it.
It's the classic can't
install rJava error message.
And instead of reading all of
this detailed information that
might help you sort out
exactly what went wrong,
I think a lot of us just
see "error" "no" "failed"
and go back into this
speculate-dither-and-fret
cycle.
So these proper debugging
tools are nerdy,
and they're technical.
And you're going to have to push
through big ugly error messages
or call stacks,
but you can do it.
So I'm going to show
you a small example
in this section
of a function I've
written called fruit_avg().
So the type of
input that it takes
is a data frame, where
we have one column
for each piece of fruit and
one row for different fruit
attributes.
So we know that a blackberry has
4 calories, it weighs 9 grams,
and my personal rating
on yumminess is 6.
And so when you pass that
object to fruit_avg()
and give it a pattern, it
will find the matching columns
and average their attributes.
So that's what it
looks like when
we're averaging two fruits.
What if I asked for melon?
Melon isn't in this data set.
So I get no fruits.
You could argue that--
found zero fruits-- like,
pluralization is really hard!
I didn't get to spend
a lot of time on this.
So that's fine.
It's not beautiful, but it's
fine for early edge case.
But here's a problem.
So if I ask for the fruits
whose name contain black,
I thought maybe there'd
be more than one,
blackberry, black currant.
I get a weird message,
like found fruits.
And then I get an error.
And the error is about rowMeans()
being applied to mini_dat.
And I'm being told that
x must be an array.
So I didn't call rowMeans().
I didn't make mini_dat.
I don't know who x is.
And so this is a common sort
of confusion situation, where
you are going to have to slowly
figure out what all of those
mean.
You're going to fiddle around
in the bowels of fruit_avg()
to figure out what's going on.
And does fruit_avg()
contain a bug?
Or did you somehow
send unexpected data?
So when I thought about
this part of the talk, which
is kind of hard to
deliver in this setting,
because you can't all do
exercises and whatnot,
I decided to take a tour
through three modes of true R
debugging.
And I'm using a death metaphor.
I think it's accurate because we
are talking about fatal errors.
So we're going to go through
some things from the left side
to the right.
And they're basically in order
of probably what you should try
and also in order of how
much control you have.
So the least amount of control
is the death certificate,
where you can just
learn a few basic facts.
The next level up is you get
to participate in an autopsy.
And you are actually allowed
to examine the subject.
And then finally, if you
haven't watched Game of Thrones,
this creature is re-animating
a lot of dead people
to create an army, but
the idea is of reanimation
or resuscitation.
So this is how I map these on
to some classic R debugging
strategies.
And we're going to go
through them in this order.
So traceback() is your first
line of defense, I guess,
where you can see what all was
called on the way to death.
So it is very much like a death
certificate, where you get some
rather spare facts.
If that doesn't allow you
to solve your problem,
you might go a little
bit more interventional.
And you can change the error
option in R so that right
before the function
exits-- like,
you're still on a
one-way ticket out--
you can do an autopsy and
inspect the call stack.
But you can't really change
the past at this point.
Whereas if you use browser()
and related techniques,
you actually interrupt things
before death is inevitable
and get a much
better opportunity
to maybe fix things.
So we're going to
go through these.
So if I call fruit_avg()
on our troublesome example,
I get the error.
You immediately would
call traceback() here.
And what you do is you read
this from the bottom up,
and it shows you the sequence
of calls that led to the error.
So you called fruit_avg().
Apparently somewhere inside
fruit_avg(), on line five,
in fact, rowMeans() got called.
And somewhere inside
rowMeans() there was a stop().
So this is called
the call stack.
And that's a term that applies
across many, many languages.
In R, we summon it with
the function traceback().
So when I decided
to do this topic,
I thought I am finally going
to get to the bottom of what
all those different terms mean.
And it turns out that you can
take any two of those words,
and you can probably
put them in any order.
And you will find some
pocket of the R community
who uses that term except
call back, which is real
and is totally different.
But you hear people talk about
the call stack, the trace back,
the stack trace, and the
back trace all the time,
and they all mean
the same thing.
An alternative view that's
coming for back traces
is from rlang.
So rlang is accumulating
more and more functionality
for developers, really, for
throwing classed errors.
But one of the
things it also offers
is some new takes at how
to present the call stack.
And that's the one
part of that area
of rlang that might be
relevant to just about anyone.
Mostly this is developer facing.
But this is an alternative
view of that same call stack.
And it's in a different order,
and there's some nice nesting.
And so this is being designed
with readability in mind.
So if you like looking
at call stacks this way,
there's something you can
do in your startup file.
And if you like using
RStudio, it also
has a really nice default
method for how to handle errors.
And it will by default show
you the base R traceback()
and then also offer
you an easy way
to get to some of the
techniques that are coming next.
So that's traceback().
So the last two techniques
I want to talk about
are the ones where you get to
intervene, either intervene
post death in the autopsy
or intervene even earlier.
And this is just a
little video that I
think totally evokes what's
going on or how it feels.
But you get to open
this hidden door
and go into this
whole world that has
a microwave and a refrigerator.
And you can you can
certainly look at things,
and you might be able
to do things in there.
That's how it feels
to be in the debugger.
It's less charming,
I have to say.
And then you come back
out, close the door,
and hopefully that hidden world
goes back to being hidden.
But that's kind
of what's going on
in these next two techniques.
So if you decide
that you actually
need to see the state of
things at the time of an error,
you can set your error option
to the recover() function.
So right as you're on
your way out the door,
execution will pause, and you're
allowed to look at frames.
And those are the
environments corresponding
to the different function calls.
So I'm going to pick 1 here.
I want to see what mini_dat is.
So we're in the usual
interactive R console.
But you know things are special
because the prompt contains
the word "Browse" and 1, which
tells us which frame we're in.
And you can print objects here.
But a lot of what people
do here is they use ls()
to see which objects exist.
Or in this case,
I'm using ls.str()
to look at each
object in the environment.
And I am particularly
interested in mini_dat
because I know it's my nemesis.
And I notice that it's
an integer vector.
And I know from
the error that it's
being sent to rowMeans(),
which I'm pretty sure needs
a two-dimensional object.
So I think many of
you, your Spidey sense
is already telling you what
the problem might be here.
If you do this recover()
work inside RStudio,
it's great because your usual
environment pane is brought
to bear on this problem.
And you can be looking at
the execution environments
of those functions in the normal
beautiful environment viewer.
But let's say-- so now I have
a theory about what's wrong.
I think the fact
that this somehow
became a vector is my problem.
But now I want to
sort of test that.
So the final, most interventional
thing you can possibly do
is we're going to use browser().
And so this last debugging
mode is most powerful
if you actually have the
source of the function
you're trying to work with.
There are ways to get
here without that.
But it works best when you do
because you'll have something
called "source references".
So that was the first look
you got at the actual source
of fruit_avg().
And what I do is I insert a
call to the browser function
in the body of the function.
And you want to insert
it before the error.
And if you knew
where the error was,
we wouldn't be having
this conversation.
So you often want to
start high, and then you
can work it lower as you
learn more about the problem.
So I'm putting it
as the first line.
And there are, as
I said, other ways
to get into a similar
world that I simply
don't have time to cover.
So in the RStudio IDE--
again, you've got
the source open--
you can set what's called
an IDE breakpoint.
And that's what
that red dot means.
And then you're not
editing your code.
So a lot of people find
that a nicer workflow.
And if you don't have the
source to a function--
maybe it's in a package
owned by someone else,
and you haven't
bothered to download
the source, or it's base R--
you can use debug() to get a
fairly similar experience.
But it's a little more
hampered by the fact
that you don't have
the actual source.
So this is a little video of me
live browser()-ing this problem.
So first thing I do is I source
a version of fruit_avg()
that has that
browser() call in it.
Then I'm going to
immediately call it
on my usual troublesome example.
And what you're going
to see is I immediately
get kicked into this
slightly different version
of the regular
interactive R console.
And the "Browse" thing
will be in the prompt.
So I can use 'n' now to
go next line, next line.
And I'm walking
through that function.
It might be someone else's
function line by line.
And finally we get to mini_dat.
So I'm going to inspect
mini_dat very exhaustively
and see what it looks like.
I'm going to see what its
dimensions, which are NULL,
because it's a vector, and
how many columns this has,
which is also NULL,
because it's a vector.
And I'm pretty sure
this is my problem.
But here's the
cool thing that you
can't do in any
other debugging mode,
is I can redefine mini_dat.
And I'm going to do
the same sub-setting.
But I'm going to specify
'drop = FALSE' so
that even if I get
just one column,
it's still going to be a
two-dimensional object.
I check the dimensions again.
And then I can
resume at execution.
And I'm going to get the error--
the message I should see.
And I'm going to get
the result I should see.
And so this is how
you sort of test
a theory or pilot a
solution to what you think
might be going wrong.
So that's what using browser()--
and there's different ways
to get into this world--
looks like.
So to conclude this
section, every time
I've talked about this before,
people come up to me afterwards
to talk about this.
They're like, it
must be in the talk.
It has to be at the talk.
So it's very easy-- and I
certainly have experienced this
myself--
to be in the browser().
You think you're really clever.
I'm going to upgrade
my debugging skills.
And you don't know how
to get back out of it.
So you will never remember this.
But it's capital Q.
If you're in RStudio,
there's also a helpful button,
a Stop button with a square that
will get you out of it.
You'll eventually learn.
And then two things that are
more proactive to know about
is if you've used
debug() on a function,
it means every time
you execute you're
going to get kicked
back into the browser(),
undebug() on the same function
as how you cancel this behavior.
And some people have been
burned by this so badly so
many times that they have
a policy of only using
debugonce().
And what it does is it will
send you into this environment
browser exactly
once, the first time
you hit that point
and then never again.
So it's sort of
self-destructing.
So those are all
good to know about.
Our last section is
more future facing.
And it's how do you create
your projects in a way
that they are less
hospitable to bugs.
And when things go wrong,
because, of course,
they're going to, you're giving
yourself more information
to help you solve it.
So if you fixed something once,
or you've seen some weird edge
behavior that causes
all hell to break loose,
do something to make sure
that that stays fixed.
And these tips are
increasingly going
to be more packaged
development focused.
Although some of it is
relevant to scripts.
But so based on the
example we just worked,
like if fruit_avg() was
in a package I maintain.
Once I make that fix,
'drop = FALSE',
I also add this
test to make sure
that the behavior
is what it should
be when we have zero fruits, one
fruit, and two fruits matching.
And so for people working
with data analysis and a data
script, this is
another hypothetical.
Like, let's imagine you're
importing fruit data
on a regular basis.
And somewhere down
in the pipeline
there's an implicit assumption
that everything's numeric.
And maybe you've been burned
by having things unexpectedly
import as character.
Once you've spent a
half day debugging that,
you should add an assertion in
your pipeline so that the next
time that happens-- because
you probably can't prevent it--
you at least know very early,
and you have a really excellent
error message for yourself.
So over time you're
going to accumulate
lots of these sorts of checks
on whether you make a data
pipeline or on a package.
And so you want to be running
them en masse and really often.
So two great big collections
of checks that you could be
running-- and this is
definitely about packages now--
is R CMD check
itself will show you
if your package is meeting
all the various criteria
enforced by CRAN.
And for the vast
majority of those,
it's a standard
you want to meet,
whether you're going to put
your package on CRAN or not,
and something you'd want
to run really often.
And then you're going
to have custom tests,
like the one I just showed
you, that uniquely tests
the functionality of your work.
So our group uses
a package called
testthat to express those
and to sort of choreograph
the running of them.
And when you set that up,
you can run just them.
And then it's also wired up
that those will run every time
R CMD check is done.
And this means you're
much more likely to run
all of your tests.
And the sooner you learn
that you broke something,
the easier it is to fix it
because usually the delta is
smaller and you're looking
in a smaller haystack.
If you only run R CMD
check every 10 months,
you've made a very big
haystack to look through.
And then the next level
up is to run those checks
not on your machine,
but on their machine.
And that pretty
much means that you
have to be using a whole
other set of practices that
are beyond this talk, but
that you are keeping your code
under version control, pushing
it to a remote version control
host, like a GitHub or
a GitLab or a BitBucket.
And you'll use something
called continuous integration.
And every time you make a
change, it will kick off,
running R CMD check, which
includes your tests, preferably
over many different
operating systems.
So you get extra credit
here if you are running it
on different operating systems.
And again, this just means
that you find errors sooner,
when they're easier to fix.
This last-- this particular
point is extremely personal.
So I have found that
there are certain patterns
I will use inside a function
or certain data structures that
later prove to be very enriched
for bugs, like bug magnets.
And when I have to
go back in and tinker
with that piece of
code, I hate it.
So for me, it's recursion and
high-dimensional data arrays,
like big dimensional data cubes.
So if you need that
abstraction to solve
your problem, absolutely, of
course, you should leave it in.
But if I'm honest with
myself, sometimes I
did this because I could.
And both of these
things, I find, make
perfect sense when
you've been thinking
about nothing but that
problem for three days.
And it just-- it's so elegant.
And then you go away.
And six months later, this
is where the bug will be.
It is not so elegant anymore.
It takes a long time to upload
all of that back into your RAM.
And so I find that if you have
some pattern like that where
you kick yourself
for using it when
you could have done something
simpler, stop doing that.
Here's a Douglas
Adams quote that I
think has a lot of relevance
to building data packages.
"The major difference between
a thing that might go wrong
and a thing that cannot possibly
go wrong is that when the thing
that cannot possibly goes wrong,
it's impossible to get at
and repair."
And so the idea I want
to talk about here
is that as you're
building things,
you will be so happy later
if you've left yourself
some kind of an access panel.
And in this case,
there's a valve here
that you can go in and
turn off or up or down.
And I'm not going to go through
all of the examples here.
But I'm going through several
packages near and dear to me.
And I'm also showing an
example from base R, where
if you're trying to
debug Excel import
or making HTTP calls
or some sort of hairy
nonstandard evaluation problem,
you have a way to flip a switch
and suddenly be getting
a lot more information.
And this is great for
package developers.
It's very useful
during development.
And then also when you're trying
to help a user debug something
and you're having that sort
of vocabulary communication
problem, you can ask them,
open the access panel,
run your problem, and send you
a lot more information that
might help you get unstuck.
My last point is about
writing error messages.
So we've come back
to where we started,
which is with the world--
or R's most famous error
message, object of type closure
is not subsettable.
My theory is that the
reason this sends people
for such a loop is
the word 'closure'
and that a lot of people
don't know what that means.
So we could also, in most cases,
use the word 'function' there.
I'm not sure if that
would immediately
make everyone love this
error message, like,
I totally know what to do now.
I can fix my problem.
But I think it removes
one communication barrier.
In the Tidyverse,
we've been trying
to create some sort of
standard for ourselves
for error messages where we
return as much information
as we have, like where
the error occurred,
the name of the object
involved if we're
pretty sure we have that
right, and maybe even a hint.
So this is a much more
controversial version
of 'object of closure
is not subsettable',
where we say I can't
subset a function for you.
Have you've forgotten to
define a variable named df?
So this is the type of
hint we give sometimes.
It's extremely dangerous,
though, because people really
trust you.
And if you're wrong,
it gets really
difficult to predict
all the different ways
people can get an error message.
If you're wrong, you're
going to send a lot of people
on a wild goose chase.
So I'm not sure that this error
is really amenable to this.
But a much cleaner
example is from dplyr.
So dplyr has a
function called filter(),
where you can ask for just
certain rows in a data set.
And it's very easy to use
the single equals sign
when you want the logical
double equals sign.
And apparently enough people
have fallen down this pothole
that the dplyr maintainers
have had mercy on all of us.
And it's pretty clear what
people mean to suggest,
maybe you need to be using
the double equals sign.
So I think of all the error
messages that have hints,
this is my favorite.
And it's the one that
has helped me the most.
So that brings us
to the end here.
I'm going to review your
troubleshooting blueprint.
So something weird happens.
I think the very first
thing you should do
is turn it off and
turn it on again.
You'll be amazed how often
your problem is gone.
If it's not gone,
try to make a reprex.
Pretend like you're going to
send it out into the world,
and you need to minimize it.
You need to write a clean
self-contained version.
Again, you will be
amazed how often
that process gets
you unstuck and leads
to a productive solution.
If that doesn't work, you will
have to dig into the error.
And I really think using
the proper debugging
tools is very useful.
And I know that I put off
that day way too long.
So if they look kind
of intimidating,
I suggest that you time box it.
So maybe say the
next time I come up
with one of these
weird situations,
I'm going to fiddle around
with these traceback(), recover(),
and browser() for 10 minutes.
And if I haven't
really gotten anywhere,
I have permission to quit
and go back to my old ways.
And I think you'll
find that with just
a little bit of usage, you get
a lot better, much more quickly.
And then finally plan
for the unexpected.
So you are clearly going to be
debugging everything you build.
I'm sorry to tell you that.
And so you might as well
build it in such a way
that when it fails, it
fails informatively.
When you break things,
you learn quickly.
And again, just make it easier
to recover from the bugs that
will inevitably come up.
So there's the short
link again if you
want to see more links about
the talk, get the slides.
They're kind of large.
So I would recommend that you
look at them on SpeakerDeck.
But I really want to give
big thanks to two people,
virtual people.
First, the Tidyverse
team has listened to me
practice parts of this
talk for many, many months.
And I have to say
that we actually
learned a lot about
debugging from each other
based on these every two or
three week conversations.
And part of why I
want to say that
is a lot of this stuff
maybe feels a bit exotic,
especially the
debugging section.
And just let it be known that
people on the Tidyverse team
learn things by talking
to each other about this.
Not everything we talked
about makes it into the talk.
It's more technical.
But people don't talk about
this enough, I've decided.
And people have cool
tricks to share with you.
And finally, I want to
thank Christine Kuper, who
created the beautiful
visual design for this talk.
And without further ado,
thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]